Chandler, Alfred D., 1918-2007. Papers, 1941-2004: A Finding Aid
Alfred D. Chandler papers, 1940-2007
Baker Library, Harvard Business School
Arch GA 12.50.1
Alfred D. Chandler, 1918-2007
125 linear ft. (284 boxes, 1 carton, 4 oversize boxes, 3 volumes, and 3 oversize folders)
The collection includes papers of Professor Alfred D. Chandler documenting his research, teaching, and other professional activities.
Provenance:
Gift of Alfred D. Chandler. The collection was received in separate accessions between 1989-2010.
Material related to General Motors was donated by Alfred D. Chandler in 1971. These papers were previously cataloged with the Baker Library Historical Collections Manuscripts Collection (MSS: 534 1908-1960). They consist of interviews, memos, drafts, and other records related to the publication of Alfred P. Sloan's book My Years with General Motors.
Restricted material has been indentified and separated. Note that box and folder lists of restricted material have been redacted. See Archivist for more information.
Related Material:
Papers of Fay Chandler, 1934-2004. Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library on the History of Women in America.
Biographical Note:
Alfred Dupont Chandler was born in Guyencourt, Delaware on September 15, 1918. He received his BA in history from Harvard College in 1940 and attended the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill from 1945 to 1946 (from which he received an MA in history in 1951). He returned to Harvard in 1946 and received his MA in 1947 and then PhD in 1952, both in history. He married Fay Martin in 1944 and had four children.
Chandler wrote his dissertation on Henry Varnum Poor, his great-grandfather, whose personal papers he discovered stored in the house of a deceased aunt. His dissertation eventually became his first book, Henry Varnum Poor, Business Editor, Analyst and Reformer, published in 1956. It was through studying Poor’s comparative analysis of railroads, the first U.S. large-scale enterprise, that Chandler began his career-long engagement with the study of change in business structure and managerial organization. He served in the U.S. Navy from 1940-1945 as Lt. Commander, which gave him valuable, first-hand experience with a giant enterprise.
Chandler was a research associate at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology from 1950-1951 and taught there from 1951-1963. In 1954 he served as academic consultant at the Naval War College, where he conceived the idea for Strategy and Structure, his second book, which was published in 1962, and won the Newcomen Award. During his time at MIT he also wrote a number of articles, served as assistant editor of four volumes of The Letters of Theodore Roosevelt, and was consulting historical advisor to Alfred P. Sloan Jr. in the writing of Sloan’s My Years with General Motors, published in 1964.
Chandler taught at Johns Hopkins University from 1963-1970, serving as chairman of the history department for four years and as director of the Center for the Study of Recent History for three years. He edited and compiled Giant Enterprise: Ford, General Motors, and the Automobile Industry, published in 1964, and The Railroads, The Nation’s First Big Business, published in 1965. He also co-edited The Changing Economic Order: Readings in American Business and Economic History, published in 1968, and edited and co-edited six volumes of The Papers of Dwight D. Eisenhower.
Chandler came to Harvard Business School in 1970. He was the Thomas Henry Carroll Ford Foundation Visiting Professor for a year and Isidor Straus Professor of Business History from 1971 to 1989. He became Isidor Straus Professor of Business History Emeritus in 1989. He published a number of books while at HBS: Pierre S. du Pont and the Making of the Modern Corporation, written with Stephen Salsbury (1971); The Visible Hand: The Managerial Revolution in American Business (1977), which won both the Pulitzer and Bancroft prizes; The Coming of Managerial Capitalism: A Casebook in the History of American Economic Institutions, written with Richard Tedlow (1985); Scale and Scope: The Dynamics of Industrial Capitalism (1990); Inventing the Electronic Century: The Epic Story of the Consumer Electronics and Computer Industries (2001); and Shaping the Industrial Century: The Remarkable Story of the Evolution of the Modern Chemical and Pharmaceutical Industries (2005). He also contributed numerous chapters and articles to books and journals, edited and co-edited a number of volumes, and served as the editor of Harvard Studies in Business History.
During his years at HBS, Chandler traveled extensively around the United States, Europe and Japan for conferences and lectures. In addition he was visiting fellow at All Souls College, Oxford (1975), visiting professor at the European Institute of Advanced Studies in Management, Brussels (1979), and Walker-Ames Visiting Professor at the University of Washington (1981).
Throughout his career, Chandler was actively engaged with numerous professional organizations and conferences, often in leadership roles. Among them were the Economic History Association, the Society for the History of Technology, the American Historical Association, the Organization of American Historians, the Massachusetts Historical Society, the Business History Conference, the Eleutherian Mills Hagley Foundation, the American Philosophical Society, the Business History Foundation, and the Council on Research in Economic History. He was chairman of the Advisory History Committee of the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission (the AEC was dismantled in 1975 and superseded by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission and the Energy Research and Development Administration) and also served on advisory boards and committees for the corporate histories of business corporations, among them, the British Petroleum Company, Alcoa, Citibank, and Du Pont’s Research and Development Division.
Alfred Chandler received honorary degrees from the University of Leuven, Belgium (1976), the University of Antwerp, Belgium (1979), Italian Academy of Business Economy (1980), Babson College, Massachusetts (1982), Ohio State University (1987), York University, Canada (1988), New England College (1992), University of Delaware (2002), and Northeastern University (2002). In 1995 he was awarded the Distinguished Service Award which is Harvard's highest honor.
Alfred Chandler died on May 9, 2007 in Cambridge, Mass.
Scope and Content Note:
The collection reflects the work and intellectual development of Alfred D. Chandler from graduate school at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and Harvard University, through his tenures at Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Johns Hopkins University, and Harvard Business School, to his position as professor emeritus. The collection covers a period of over sixty years during which Chandler studied the historical evolution and organizational development of the modern corporation.
The collection includes many of his lecture and seminar notes and almost the entire body of his professional correspondence. The collection documents his and others’ research on and interpretation of the evolution of the modern corporation; his editorial work on the papers of Theodore Roosevelt and Dwight D. Eisenhower; his role as trustee and president of the Economic History Association and as executive board member of the Organization of American Historians; and his involvement with many other professional and scholarly organizations, especially in contributing to business history conferences, editing papers, and overseeing their publication. The collection includes manuscript versions of his and others’ work. It is also rich in research material gathered in the course of his comparative studies of corporate structure and its development in the United States and in other industrial economies, including a wealth of research notes taken and photocopies made from records in institutional and company archives.
The collection is divided into eleven series. The first five represent stages in Chandler’s career and institutional affiliation; the sixth consists of audio-visual material; the seventh of restricted Harvard University and Harvard Business School administration records; the eighth of restricted Harvard University and Harvard Business School student and personnel records; the ninth of biographical materials; the tenth of ephemera; and the final of offprints of publications by Alfred Chandler. Contents of both restricted series were separated according to Harvard University guidelines.
Series Outline
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series I. Early Professional Work, 1940-1965
Subseries A. Military Record, 1941-1965
Subseries B. University of North Carolina, 1945-1946
Subseries C. Harvard University, 1940-1950
Series II. Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) and Johns Hopkins University, 1949-1978
Subseries A. MIT Correspondence and Subject Files, 1951-1965
Subseries B. MIT Research and Writing, 1949-1967
Subseries C. MIT Research and Writing: Alfred P. Sloan Autobiography: General Motors, 1954-1960
Subseries D. MIT Administration and Program, 1953-1963
Subseries E. MIT Teaching, 1951-1962
Subseries F. MIT External Activities: Teaching, 1954-1963
Subseries G. MIT External Activities: Conferences, 1956-1963
Subseries H. MIT External Activities: Memberships, 1957-1963
Subseries I. Johns Hopkins University Correspondence and Subject Files, 1963-1978
Subseries J. Johns Hopkins University Research and Writing, 1958-1972
Subseries K. Johns Hopkins University Teaching, 1963-1970
Subseries L. Johns Hopkins University Administration and Programs, 1964-1971
Subseries M. Johns Hopkins University External Activities: Conferences, 1964-1972
Subseries N. Johns Hopkins University External Activities: Memberships, 1956-1972
Series III. Harvard Business School- Active Tenure, 1968-1991
Subseries A. HBS Correspondence and Subject Files, Active Tenure, 1968-1988
Subseries B. HBS Correspondence and Subject Files, Transition, 1978-1991
Subseries C. HBS Research and Writing, General, 1970-1988
Subseries D. HBS Research Material: Daniel Bell Fortune Magazine Files, 1948-1982
Subseries E. HBS Teaching, 1970-1989
Subseries F. HBS External Activities: Conferences, 1971-1989
Subseries G. HBS External Activities: Memberships, 1968-1987
Series IV. Harvard Business School, Emeritus, 1973-2007
Subseries A. HBS Emeritus Correspondence and Subject Files, 1973-2007
Subseries B. HBS Emeritus Research and Writing, 1988-2005
Subseries C. HBS Emeritus Conferences, Addresses, Talks, Lectures, 1989-2003
Subseries D. HBS Emeritus Memberships, 1982-1993
Series V. Appointment Calendars, 1977–1987
Series VI. Audio-Visual Records, 1940-2007
Subseries A. Photographs, circa 1940-1987
Subseries B. Dictabelt Recordings, ca. 1965
Subseries C. Videos, 1990-1995
Series VII. HBS and HU Administration and Program Records [Restricted], 1959-1998
Subseries A. General, 1970-1998
Subseries B. Harvard Studies in Business History, 1959-1990
Subseries C. Administration and Program Records Removed from Active Tenure Teaching Records, 1971-1998
Subseries D. Business History Foundation: General, 1947-1991
Subseries E. Business History Foundation: Great Northern Project, 1954-1988
Series VIII. HBS and HU Student and Personnel Records [Restricted], 1958-2001
Subseries A. HBS and HU Student and Personnel Records, 1971-2001
Subseries B. Student Information Removed from Business History Seminar Series, 1971-1984
Subseries C. Confidential Records, 1958-1985
Series IX. Biographical Records, 1947-2007
Subseries A. Biographical Materials, 1971-2007
Subseries B. Awards and Honorary Degrees, 1947-2003
Series X. Ephemera, 1980-1991
Series XI. Offprints, 1949-2005
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I. Early Professional Work, 1940-1965
  This series documents Alfred Chandler's early educational and professional work and includes materials that reflect Chandler’s service in the U.S. Military, his work as a graduate student at the University of North Carolina Chapel Hill (MA 1951), and undergraduate and graduate work at Harvard University (BA 1940, MA 1947, PhD 1952). Types of materials include course work, military records, notes, exams and papers. The series is organized into three subseries: A. Military Records, B. University of North Carolina, and C. Harvard University.
  - Subseries A. Military Record, 1941-1965
    This subseries consists of material kept by Alfred Chandler while serving in the U.S. Navy and includes his Officer Service Record, documentation of his release from active duty, commendation, veteran's benefit materials, and photographs.
    - Letter from parents, January 5, 1942 (Box 253, f. 11)
    - Commendation, March 5, 1946 (Box 1, f. 1)
    - Insurance, 1946 (Box 1, f. 2)
    - Officer Service Record, 1945-1955 (Box 1, f. 3)
    - Photographs, circa 1945 (Box 196)
    - Information about photographs, circa 1965 (Box 1, f. 4-5)
    - Release from Active Duty, 1945 (Box 1, f. 6)
    - Veteran’s Benefits- Education, circa 1945-1949 (Box 1, f. 7)
  - Subseries B. University of North Carolina, 1945-1946
    This subseries consists of syllabi, reading lists, exams, class notes, reading notes and other course materials kept by Alfred Chandler while a graduate student at the University of North Carolina.
    - History 149: The American Colonies, 1606-1689: Reading List, Fall 1945 (Box 1, f. 8)
    - History 149: The American Colonies, 1606-1689: Class Notes, Fall 1945 (Box 1, f. 9-10)
    - History 149: The American Colonies, 1606-1689: Paper, Notes, Fall 1945 (Box 1, f. 11)
    - History 163: The Antebellum South: Syllabus, Notes, Fall 1945 (Box 1, f. 12)
    - History 150: The American Colonies, 1689-1783: Reading List, Spring 1946 (Box 1, f. 13)
    - History 150: The American Colonies, 1689-1783: Class Notes, Spring 1946 (Box 1, f. 14-15)
    - History 164: The South Since the Civil War (Dr. Green): Reading List, Syllabus, Spring 1946 (Box 1, f. 16)
    - History 201: History of American Historical Writing, Spring 1946 (Box 1, f. 17)
    - Seminar Reading Lists, Spring 1946 (Box 1, f. 18)
    - Sociology 180: Folk-Regional Sociology: Syllabus, Reading List, Class Material, Notes, Spring 1946 (Box 1, f. 19)
    - Sociology 186: Population (Rupert B. Vance): Class Notes, Spring 1946 (Box 1, f. 20)
    - Sociology 186: Population (Rupert B. Vance): Reading List, Class Notes, Spring 1946 (Box 1, f. 21)
    - Sociology 185: The Negro: Class Notes, Exams, Summer 1946 (Box 1, f. 22)
  - Subseries C. Harvard University, 1940-1950
    This subseries consists of Alfred Chandler's graduate school papers, syllabi, reading lists, exams, class notes, and reading notes. This subseries includes of syllabi, reading lists, exams, class notes, reading notes and other materials kept by Alfred Chandler while a graduate student at Harvard University. The subseries also includes Chandler’s undergraduate honors thesis titled, “The Campaign of 1876 in South Carolina” presented in March 1940; and Chandler's lecture notes and other material from his position as assistant to R.G. Albion in teaching a course in Maritime History.
    Arranged chronologically by course.
    - Undergraduate honors thesis, "The Campaign of 1876 in South Carolina," 15 March 1940 (Vol. 1)
    - Notes for undergraduate honors thesis, "The Campaign of 1876 in South Carolina," 15 March 1940 (Vol. 2)
    - History 63: American Social and Intellectual History: Class Notes, Fall 1946 (Box 1, f. 24-26)
    - History 63: American Social and Intellectual History: Reading Notes, Fall 1946 (Box 2, f. 1-2)
    - Social Relations 62: Immigrant Culture in Transition: Class Notes, Fall 1946 (Box 2, f. 3-5)
    - Social Relations 62: Immigrant Culture in Transition: Syllabus, Exam, Reading Notes, Fall 1946 (Box 2, f. 6)
    - History 60a: American Colonial History (Samuel Eliot Morrison): Syllabus, Notes, Exam, 1946-1947 (Box 2, f. 7)
    - History 60a: American Colonial History (Samuel Eliot Morrison): Class Notes, 1946-1947 (Box 2, f. 8-9)
    - History 160a: Critique of Mr. Chandler, Dec. 1946 (Box 2, f. 10)
    - History 60b: The American Revolution: Syllabus, Reading Notes, Exam, Spring 1947 (Box 2, f. 11)
    - History 60b: The American Revolution (Samuel Eliot Morison): Class Notes, Spring 1947 (Box 2, f. 12-13)
    - History 63b: Reading Notes, Spring 1947 (Box 2, f. 14)
    - History 63b: Class Notes, Spring 1947 (Box 2, f. 15-16)
    - Social Relations 32: Social Structure of the U.S.: Class Notes, 1947 (Box 2, f. 17)
    - Social Relations 32: Social Structure of the U.S.: Reading Notes, Spring 1947 (Box 2, f. 18)
    - Social Relations 32: Social Structure of the U.S.: Readings, Spring 1947 (Box 2, f. 19)
    - Social Relations 32: Social Structure of the U.S.: Term Paper, Spring 1947 (Box 3, f. 1)
    - Social Relations 32: Social Structure of the U.S.: Exams, Spring 1947 (Box 3, f. 2)
    - History 64a: American Diplomatic History: Class Notes, Fall 1947 (Box 3, f. 3)
    - History 64b: The U.S. as a World Power, 1898-1939: Syllabus, Class Notes, 1947-1948 (Box 3, f. 4)
    - Reading Notes (found after History 64b Class Notes) (Box 3, f. 5-6)
    - Social Relations 30: Class Notes, Fall 1947 (Box 3, f. 7)
    - Economics 61: Class Notes, 1947-1948 (Box 3, f. 8)
    - History 6: Greek History: Class Notes, 1947-1948 (Box 3, f. 9-10)
    - History 6: Greek History: Papers, 1947-1948 (Box 3, f. 11-12)
    - History 6: Greek History: Reading Notes, 1947-1948 (Box 3, f. 13-14)
    - History 6: Greek History: Note cards, 1947-1948 (Box 3, f. 15)
    - History 136: Maritime History (R.G. Albion): Lecture Notes, Fall 1948 (Box 3, f. 16)
    - History 136: Maritime History (R.G. Albion): Lecture Notes, Spring 1949 (Box 3, f. 17-18)
    - History 136/168: Maritime History (R.G. Albion): Notes, Reading Lists, Exams, 1948-1950 (Box 3, 19-20)
    - History 69: Class Notes, undated (Box 4, f. 1)
    - "Dahlgren, DuPont, and the Civil War Nitre Shortage" (pages missing), undated (Box 4, f. 2-3)
      Paper written by Alfred Chandler
    - "Dahlgren, DuPont, and the Civil War Nitre Shortage" notes, undated (Box 4, f. 4)
    - Seminar 162b: Professor Merle, undated (Box 4, f. 5)
    - MA degree language exams and reports, 1947 (Box 4, f. 6)
    - Unidentified notes, undated (Box 4, f. 7)
- Series II. Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Johns Hopkins University, 1949-1978
  This series consists of papers related to Alfred Chandler’s teaching, research, and writing activities while a faculty member at Massachusetts Institute of Technology (1950-1963) and Johns Hopkins University (1963-1970). Material related to MIT includes correspondence and subject files, research and writings, including Chandler’s contribution to Alfred P. Sloan’s autobiography, MIT teaching and administrative records, and conferences and professional memberships.Material related to Johns Hopkins University includes correspondence and subject files, research and writings, teaching and administrative records, and conferences and professional memberships.
  - Subseries A. MIT Correspondence and Subject Files, 1951-1965
    This subseries consists of Alfred Chandler's correspondence and subject files kept while teaching at MIT where he taught from 1950-1963. The correspondents include Chandler's colleagues, students, fellow scholars, business executives, family, and friends. The subjects covered include: Chandler's graduate degree; grants; the research of others; Chandler's work, in particular his biographies of Henry Varnum Poor and Pierre S. du Pont; his research on Standard Oil, General Motors, and the DuPont Company; invitations to apply for teaching positions, to present papers, and to write reviews; and Chandler family matters. Of particular interest are Chandler's communications with Professor Howard R. Bartlett which list his accomplishments and summarize his research projects and objectives. Correspondence can also be found in each of the other series.
    - A: Abaya-Appleton (Box 4, f. 8)
    - Aitken, Hugh G. J., 1952-1957 (Box 4, f. 9)
    - American Historical Association, 1957-1961 (Box 4, f. 10)
    - American Philosophical Society, 1956-1957 (Box 4, f. 11)
    - Anderson, George, 1956 (Box 4, f. 12)
    - Anderson, Oscar E., Jr., 1961-1962 (Box 4, f. 13)
    - Andreano, Ralph, 1962-1963 (Box 4, f. 14)
    - B: Badner-Brock (Box 4, f. 15)
    - Bartlett, Howard R., 1951-1963 (Box 4, f. 16)
    - Bennett, Howard, 1956-1963 (Box 4, f. 17-18)
    - Benson, Lee, 1960 (Box 4, f. 19)
    - Beveridge Prize, 1959 (Box 4, f. 20)
    - Blum, John, 1955-1960 (Box 4, f. 21)
    - Brayman, Harold, 1957-1961 (Box 4, f. 22)
    - Brooks, E.P., 1955-1959 (Box 4, f. 23)
    - Bruchey, Stuart, 1959-1963 (Box 4, f. 24)
    - Burchard, John E., 1953-1960 (Box 4, f. 25)
    - Bushman, Richard L., 1963 (Box 4, f. 26)
    - Business Census Proposal, 1962 (Box 4, f. 27)
    - Business Histories: Bigelow-Sandford and McGraw-Hill, 1949-1953 (Box 4, f. 28-29)
    - Business History Volumes: McGraw-Hill, 1958 (Box 4, f. 30)
    - Business History Volumes: Arthur Cole, 1956 (Box 4, f. 31)
    - Business Organization Research, 1957-1963 (Box 4, f. 32-34)
    - C: Campbell-Curtin (Box 5, f. 1)
    - Chandler, Alfred D., Sr., 1951-1962 (Box 5, f. 2)
    - Chandler, Tertius, 1957-1976 (Box 5, f. 3-5)
    - Claremont Graduate School, 1957 (Box 5, f. 6)
    - Cochran, Thomas C., 1955-1962 (Box 5, f. 7)
    - Cochran, Thomas C.: Collaboration with Alfred D. Chandler and Arthur Cole, 1961-1962 (Box 5, f. 8)
    - Cole, Arthur H.: Collaboration with Alfred D. Chandler and Thomas Cochran, 1961-1962 (Box 5, f. 9-12)
    - Cole, Arthur H., 1952-1960 (Box 5, f. 13-14)
    - Columbia University, 1961-1963 (Box 5, f. 15)
    - D: Davenport-Dupree (Box 5, f. 16)
    - Dale, Ernest, 1957-1960 (Box 5, f. 17)
    - F: Ferris Fretwell (Box 5, f. 18)
    - Farnham, Wallace D., 1957-1963 (Box 5, f. 19)
    - Florida, Board of Control of, 1961 (Box 5, f. 20)
    - G: Galambos-Gutman (Box 5, f. 21)
    - Gibb, George S., 1954-1961 (Box 5, f. 22)
    - Ginger, Ray, 1953-1961 (Box 5, f. 23)
    - Gomberg, William, 1963 (Box 5, f. 24)
    - Grantham, Dewey, 1956-1958 (Box 5, f. 25)
    - Green, Fletcher M., 1951-1955 (Box 5, f. 26)
    - H: Haefele-Higham (Box 6, f. 1)
    - H: Hill-Hulme (Box 6, f. 2)
    - Harper and Row, Publishers, 1958-1962 (Box 6, f. 3)
    - Harvard University Press, 1951-1964 (Box 6, f. 4)
    - Hays, Samuel P., 1961-1963 (Box 6, f. 5)
    - Hidy, Ralph W., 1956-1962 (Box 6, f. 6)
    - Heaton, Herbert, 1952-1957 (Box 6, f. 7)
    - Herbert and Dial, Attorneys: Cat Island Suit, 1953-1954 (Box 6, f. 8)
    - Hill and Wang, Inc., Publishers, 1964 (Box 6, f. 9)
    - History of American Management Project, 1961-1962 (Box 6, f. 10)
    - Illinois, Univ. of-Jones (Box 6, f. 11)
    - Johns Hopkins University, 1963-1965 (Box 6, f. 12-14)
    - Johnson, Arthur, 1959-1963 (Box 6, f. 15)
    - Journal of Economic History, 1956-1961 (Box 6, f. 16)
    - K: Kansas, Univ. of-Kopald (Box 6, f. 17)
    - Kemmerer, Donald, 1958 (Box 6, f. 18)
    - Kirkland, Edward C., 1953-1962 (Box 6, f. 19)
    - Kranzberg, Melvin, 1956-1957 (Box 6, f. 20)
    - L: LaRue-Lyons (Box 6, f. 21)
    - Little, J.J., and Ives Company, Inc., 1960-1961 (Box 6, f. 22)
    - Longwood Library, 1958-1961 (Box 6, f. 23)
    - M: Macmillan-Meyer (Box 6, f. 24)
    - M: Michigan-Myers (Box 6, f. 25)
    - Mahoney, Tom H.D., 1961-1962 (Box 6, f. 26)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1950-1958 (Box 6, f. 27)
    - Mathias, Peter, 1956-1962 (Box 6, f. 28)
    - Miller, William, 1952-1962 (Box 6, f. 29)
    - N: Nantucket-Norton (Box 6, f. 30)
    - Naval War College, 1954-1958 (Box 6, f. 31)
    - Navy, Dept. of the, 1951-1955 (Box 6, f. 32)
    - Neu, Irene D., 1956-1957 (Box 6, f. 33)
    - Newberry Library, 1953-1955 (Box 6, f. 34)